Finding Aid for Richard Z. Goehle Personal Papers and Esenwein and Johnson Records, 1852-1942 (bulk 1882-1942)
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Richard Z. Goehle Personal Papers and Esenwein & Johnson Records
1852 - 1942
1882 - 1942
Mss. C68-3
Goehle, Richard Z. (Richard Zacharias)
17 boxes (8.5 linear feet)
The records of personal papers of Richard Z. Goehle and family between 1852-1966, and the architectural firm of Esenwein & Johnson represents the accumulated archives of the firm between 1891 and 1966.
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The Richard Z. Goehle Personal Papers and Esenwein & Johnson Records, 1852-1942 (bulk 1882-1942), are open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Dolce, Joseph S.; unknown; 1968/03/22; 68-765
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Richard Z. Goehle was the business manager of the Buffalo architectural firm of Esenwein & Johnson. He was the son of Carl August Goehle (1836-1917), a teacher and musician who emigrated from Germany in the 1850's and settled in Buffalo, where he resided for many years on Genesee Street. The elder Goehle and his wife Augusta had ten children besides Richard. Much family correspondence in Series I/Subseries A contains letters by those family members or references to them. The children of Carl and Augusta are listed below:
Mrs. John Knuebel (husband of Rev. John Knuebel)
Thelma (Mrs. Henry C. Gram; husband employed by Coca-Cola Company, Cleveland, Ohio)
Hulda (Mrs. Peter Maul; husband was a judge)
Hugo (Cedarburg, Wisconsin)
Alfred (Principal, Buffalo School 15)
Otto (physician, Cleveland, Ohio; wife, Mary after 1941
Richard Z. (Business manager, Esenwein & Johnson)
August E.
Agnes
Hedwig
Emma.
Richard Z. Goehle's personal papers, which make up over half of this collection, indicate that he lived on Main Street in Ebenezer (in the town of West Seneca) and owned property in that area as well as in Canada. Kathleen F. Bell, a secretary at Esenwein & Johnson, became Richard Z. Goehle's wife.
Historical Note
Esenwein & Johnson was a Buffalo architectural firm of international repute. It was formed in 1897 with the partnership of August Carl Esenwein (1856-1926) and James Addison Johnson (1865-1939), and had its main offices in the Ellicott Square Building in Buffalo.
Records indicate that the early years of the firm were indeed prosperous, but in the 1930's, after the death of Esenwein and the onset of the depression, commissions and revenues declined. In 1932 Johnson entered into a new partnership with B. Frank Kelly, though the firm continued under the former name of Esenwein & Johnson. Generally, growing debts and unpaid salaries were the rule during the 1930's and early 1940's until June 1942, when records of the firm cease.
August Carl Esenwein
August Carl Esenwein was born in Wuerttemberg, Germany in 1856 and was educated in architecture and engineering at Stuttgart Polytechnic University, receiving his degree in 1879. After working in Paris as a draftsman for two years, he immigrated to the United States and served an architectural apprenticeship as a draftsman for a Buffalo firm. Subsequently he was employed by the engineering department of the Delaware and Lackawanna Railroad. During that time he entered a design contest for the Music Hall and won first prize; he later supervised construction of that building. Upon leaving the railroad, he worked as an independent architect until November 27, 1897, when he formed the partnership with Johnson.
Esenwein was a member of the board of eight architects for the Pan-American Exposition; he himself designed the Temple of Music (1901). Other notable accomplishments from the firm of Esenwein & Johnson are the Harlow Curtiss mansion on Delaware Avenue (1897, later housing the International Institute); Lafayette High School (1903); the Calumet Building, with its intricate terra cotta ornamentation (1906); the General Electric Tower (1912); later the Niagara Mohawk Building), said to have been inspired by the electric tower at the Pan-American Exposition; the Elephant House at the Buffalo Zoo (1912); and the Buffalo Museum of Science (1929).
James A. Johnson
James A. Johnson was an assistant in the firm of McKim, Mead & White before joining Esenwein; his specialty became ornament. Two architectural projects that most Powerfully demonstrate Johnson's skills in that area are the Niagara Mohawk Building (1912), with its unusual external motifs featuring electric motors and generators, said to be precursors of Art Deco ornamentation; and the spectacular marble mosaic floor of the Ellicott Square Building, installed in 1929. (Plans and contracts for the floor can be found in the present collection, box 10, folder 5.)
Scope and Content Note
Personal correspondence and financial records of Richard Z. Goehle, including bills, receipts, bank records and papers concerning Canadian property; Goehle family papers, including correspondence, notes, and account books of Carl A. Goehle, 1852-1917, and notebooks of Hulda and August Goehle, ca. 1882-1894; and financial records of Camp Acres Poultry Farm (Ebenezer, N.Y.). Also, records of the architectural firm of Esenwein & Johnson, including job contracts, specifications and plans, 1898-1940; records concerning lease of office space in Ellicott Square Building, 1897-1926; partnership with B. Frank Kelly, 1932; and bank records, employee tax records, account books and ledgers, 1910-1942. Includes plan of marble mosaic floor for Ellicott Square Building, designed by James A. Johnson and W.W. Kent, 1930.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
I. Papers of Richard Z. Goehle and Family
II. Esenwein & Johnson Records.
Within each series the files are subdivided into subseries.
Container List
- Papers of Richard Z. Goehle and Family 1852-1966, I.
  Series I is divided into six subseries:
  I.A. Correspondence
  I.B. Financial Records
  I.C. Camp Acres Poultry Farm
  I.D. Records Concerning Canadian Property
  I.E. Goehle Family Papers
  I.F. Photographs, Plans, and Personal papers.
  - Correspondence, 1894-1966, I.A.
    Arranged chronologically
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1894-1905 (Box-folder 1.1)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1911-15 (Box-folder 1.2)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1916-17 (Box-folder 1.3)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1918-19 (Box-folder 1.4)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1920, 1922, 1926-1927, 1929 (Box-folder 1.5)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1931-1933 (Box-folder 1.6)
    - Correspondence re: investment in Precious Metals Production Syndicate, 1934 (Box-folder 1.7)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 1.8)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1.9)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 1.10)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 1.11)
    - Correspondence re: Peter Maul monument, Holy Rest Cemetery, Pine Hill, 1941 (Box-folder 1.12)
    - R. Z. Goehle correspondence, 1954, 1965-1966 and undated (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Financial Records, 1894-1950, I.B.
    Arranged alphabetically within chronological periods.
    - A, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.1)
    - B, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.2)
    - C-E, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.3)
    - F, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.4)
    - G-H, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.5)
    - I-L, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.6)
    - M-P, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.7)
    - R-V, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.8)
    - W-Z, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 2.9)
    - A-B, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 2.10)
    - C-F, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 2.12)
    - G-I, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 2.13)
    - J-M, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.1)
    - N-O, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - P-S, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.3)
    - T-V, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.4)
    - W, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - X-Z, 1894-1914 (Box-folder 3.6)
    - A-D, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 3.7)
    - E-I, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 3.8)
    - J-N, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 3.9)
    - P-T, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 4.1)
    - U-Z, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 4.2)
    - A-F, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 4.3)
    - G-L, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - M-Z, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 4.5)
    - A-I, 1930-1934 (Box-folder 4.6)
    - M-Z, 1930-1934 (Box-folder 4.7)
    - A-F, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 4.8)
    - G-L, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 4.9)
    - M-O, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 4.10)
    - P-U, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 4.11)
    - A-I, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 5.1)
    - J-O, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 5.2)
    - P-Z, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 5.3)
    - Bills and receipts, undated (Box-folder 5.4)
    - Checkbook registers, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 5.5)
    - Checkbook stubs, 1894-1905 (Box-folder 5.6)
    - Checkbook stubs, May 8, 1946-Nov. 9, 1949 (Box-folder 5.7)
    - Bank statements, Jan.-Sep. 1939 and Oct. 1947-Jan. 1950 (Box-folder 5.8)
    - Cancelled checks, 1939 (Box-folder 5.9)
    - Cancelled checks, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 5.10)
    - Cancelled checks, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 5.11)
    - Cancelled checks, 1949-1950, [Bound Volume] (Box 6)
  - Camp Acres Poultry Farm Records, 1919-1920, I.C.
    Arranged alphabetically by payee.
    - A (Box-folder 6.1)
    - B (Box-folder 6.2)
    - C (Box-folder 6.3)
    - D (Box-folder 6.4)
    - F (Box-folder 6.5)
    - G (Box-folder 6.6)
    - H (Box-folder 6.7)
    - I-K (Box-folder 6.8)
    - L (Box-folder 7.1)
    - M (Box-folder 7.2)
    - N-O (Box-folder 7.3)
    - P (Box-folder 7.4)
    - Q-R (Box-folder 7.5)
    - S (Box-folder 7.6)
    - T-V (Box-folder 7.7)
    - W (Box-folder 7.8)
    - Cancelled checks and bank statements, 1919 (Box-folder 7.9)
    - Account book, 1919 (Box-folder 7.10)
    - Water contract, 1919 (Box-folder 7.11)
  - Records Concerning Canadian Property, 1927-1939, I.D.
    - Records Concerning Canadian Property, 1927-1939 (Box-folder 7.12-7.13)
  - Goehle Family Papers, 1856-1930; I.E.
    Some items in German.
    - Carl A. Goehle: Account book, 1884-1901 (Box 8)
    - [Carl A. Goehle?]: expense account book, 1883-1886 (Box-folder 8.1)
    - [Carl A. Goehle?]: autograph album, 1856-1860 (Box-folder 8.2)
    - Carl A. Goehle: teaching notes and other papers, 1862-1863 and undated (Box-folder 8.3)
    - Carl A. Goehle: insurance policy, 1863 (Box-folder 8.4)
    - Carl A. Goehle: correspondence and notes, 1882-1917 and undated (Box-folder 8.5)
    - 3 Miscellaneous date books, 1887-1888 and undated (Box-folder 8.6)
    - Biology notes and drawings, circa 1906 (Box-folder 8.7)
    - Travelog of the Five Beach-Nuts (anonymous typescript), August 9th to 23rd, 1930 (Box-folder 8.8)
    - School attendance book, 1852-1863, [Located between boxes 8 and 9]
    - August E. Goehle: notebooks, [1890-1893], [ 1894] and [ 1904?] (Box-folder 9.1)
    - August E. Goehle: Public School 47 grade reports, 1895-1897 German lesson notes, 1930 (Box-folder 9.2)
    - Hulda Goehle: autograph book, ca. 1882 notebooks, circa 1885 (Box-folder 9.3)
    - Hulda Goehle: notebook on Rhetoric, State Normal School (Buffalo), 1889-1890 (Box-folder 9.4)
    - Hulda Goehle: 4 notebooks, undated (Box-folder 9.5)
    - [Hulda Goehle?]: notebook on physiology, undated (Box-folder 9.6)
    - Wm. Weinbach: notebook on Old Testament history, undated (in German) (Box-folder 9.7)
  - Photographs, Plans, and Personal Papers, circa 1918-1939, I.F.
    - Miscellaneous building plans, undated (Box-folder 9.8)
    - Unidentified photographs, undated (one small portrait labeled "Christian Grossberger") (Box-folder 9.9)
    - K.F. Bell: signed note re The Whistle Bottling Co., Cleveland, Ohio, undated (Box-folder 9.10)
    - Papers pertaining to World War I bond drive, 1918 (Box-folder 9.11)
- Esenwein & Johnson records, 1891-1942, II.
  Series II is divided into five subseries:
  II.A. Job Specifications, Contracts, and Plans
  II.B. Legal Papers
  II.C. Financial Records
  II.D. Correspondence, Printed Matter, and Financial Reports
  II.E.Subseries E. Job Card Files.
  - Job Specifications, Contracts, and Plans, 1898-1940, II.A.
    Alphabetical by job name.
    - Lists of job numbers, undated (Box-folder 10.1)
    - Calihan, Leo (apt. bldg., Rochester): specifications, 1940 (Box-folder 10.2)
    - City Bank Building: TLS and invoices, 1898 (Box-folder 10.3)
    - [Elk Place and First Street]: field notes, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 10.4)
    - Ellicott Square Building {mosaic floor): specifications, contract and plan, 1930 (Box-folder 10.5)
    - Ellicott Square Building (elevators, building and electrical changes): contracts, 1933 (Box-folder 10.6)
    - Erie County (miscellaneous jobs): payment receipts, 1907 (Box-folder 10.7)
    - Masten Park High School: contract, 1912 (Box-folder 10.8)
    - Metzger, Alfred J. (house, Ebenezer, NY): specifications, 1914 (Box-folder 10.9)
    - Nagel, Fred C. (roller skating rink, Evans, NY): specifications, 1938 (Box-folder 10.10)
    - Portage Hotel (Akron, OH): specifications, 1926 (Box-folder 10.11)
    - Prince Edward Hotel (Windsor, Ont.): specifications, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 10.12)
    - Sagamore Hotel (Rochester): specifications for alterations, 1939 (Box-folder 10.13)
    - Summer-Linwood Medical Building: Financial and contract booklet (9 cc.) (Box-folder 10.14)
    - Summer-Linwood Medical Building: contracts 1932- 1934 (Box-folder 10.15)
    - Builders uniform subcontract (blank), 1906 (Box-folder 10.16)
  - Legal papers 1897-1939, II.B.
    - Records pertaining to lease of Ellicott Square Bldg. office space, 1897-1926 (Box-folder 11.1)
    - Miscellaneous papers pertaining to the partners, 1897-1931 and undated (Box-folder 11.2)
    - Partnership agreement (J.A. Johnson and B.F. Kelly), 1932 (2 cc.)7 and certificate of continued use of partnership "Esenwein & Johnson," 1939 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - Financial Records, 1891-1941, II.C.
    The files in subseries C are further divided into four categories: Bank records, Tax and Social Security records, Ledgers and account books, and Time books.
    - Bank records
      - Bank account records, 1891-1901 (Box-folder 11.4)
      - Cancelled checks, 1898-1904; checkbook stubs, 1903- 1904 (Box-folder 11.5)
    - Tax and Social Security records
      - Social Security payroll book, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 11.6)
      - Employee tax records, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 11.7)
    - Ledgers and account books
      - Office account ledger, 1910-1931, [Bound Volume] (Box 11)
      - Check account book, 1921-1928 (Box-folder 12.1)
      - Check record book, Nov. 1931-Sept. 1933 (Box-folder 12.2)
      - Check record book, Oct. 1933-Aug. 1935 (Box-folder 12.3)
      - Check record book, Sept. 1935-Dec. 1936 (Box-folder 12.4)
      - Statements of expenses and receipts, 1933-1937 (Box-folder 12.5)
      - Ledger of checks received and paid, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 12.6)
      - Ledger of checks received and paid, 1939-1942 (Box-folder 12.7)
      - 1: Office account book, 1931-1942 (A-O) (Box-folder 13.1)
      - 1: Office account book, 1931-1942 (P-Z) (Box-folder 13.2)
    - Time books
      - Employee time book, 1897 (Box-folder 13.3)
      - Job time book, 1910-1931 (with index and schedule of wages) (Box-folder 13.4)
      - Employee time book, 1939-1942 (Box-folder 13.5)
      - Time book and payroll, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 13.6)
  - Correspondence, Printed Matter, and Financial reports, 1925-1930; II.D.
    - Charles H. Kimpel: correspondence re hotel construction, 1929 (Box-folder 13.7)
    - Specifications of Steelcrete Vault by Consolidated Expanded Metal Cos., ca. 1925 (Box-folder 13.8)
    - Associated Buffalo Architects, Inc.: Report on audit and financial statements, 1927-1930 (Box-folder 13.9)
  - Job Card Files, ca.1897-1942, II.E.
    - Job files, alphabetical by job name; cards record job descriptions and charges for architectural services. (Box 14)
    - Contractor files, alphabetical by job name; cards record contractors involved and their charges (and sometimes office costs). Two alphabetical series. (Box 15-17)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Goehle, Carl A. (Carl August), 1836-1917; Johnson, James A., 1865-1939; Kent, William Winthrop, 1860-1955; Esenwein & Johnson (Buffalo, N.Y.); Camp Acres Poultry Farm (Ebenezer, N.Y.); Buffalo History Museum
Subject Terms
Kelly, B. Frank; Ellicott Square Building (Buffalo, N.Y.); Architects--New York (State)--Buffalo
Genre Terms
Photographs; Diaries